Guide to the Adelaide Johnson Papers, 1884-1945 and undated RL.11025
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Adelaide Johnson papers
1884-1945 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Johnson, Adelaide, 1859-1955
RL.11025
0.4 Linear Feet
Adelaide Johnson, 1859-1955, was a suffragist, artist, and sculptor. Her original name was Sarah Adeline Johnson; she changed her name to Adelaide in 1878. Collection incorporates primarily Adelaide Johnson's working materials related to her sculpture of Lucretia Mott, Susan B. Anthony, and Elizabeth Cady Stanton that is located at the United States Capitol building, with focus on Susan B. Anthony. There are cabinet cards of Johnson's plaster casts, cabinet cards of Anthony and Anthony and Stanton, several signed, along with albumen, gelatin deveoping-out paper, and matte collodion printing-out paper prints of Anthony; two silhouettes of Mott; a few letters to Johnson; biographical information about her; and related published materials. There are also exhibit labels for the first exhibition to be held at Elizabeth Cady Stanton's House after it was acquired by the Women's Rights National Park at Seneca Falls, curated by Lisa Unger Baskin in 1986 or 1987, and featuring the Johnson materials. The exhibit was also displayed at the Sophia Smith Collection for a Berkshire Conference in on History of Women.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Collection Overview
Collection incorporates primarily Adelaide Johnson's working materials related to her sculpture of Lucretia Mott, Susan B. Anthony, and Elizabeth Cady Stanton that is located at the United States Capitol building, with focus on Susan B. Anthony. There are cabinet cards of Johnson's plaster casts, cabinet cards of Anthony and Anthony and Stanton, several signed, along with albumen, gelatin deveoping-out paper, and matte collodion printing-out paper prints of Anthony; two silhouettes of Mott; a few letters to Johnson; biographical information about her; and related published materials. There are also exhibit labels for the first exhibition to be held at Elizabeth Cady Stanton's House after it was acquired by the Women's Rights National Park at Seneca Falls, curated by Lisa Unger Baskin in 1986 or 1987, and featuring the Johnson materials. The exhibit was also displayed at the Sophia Smith Collection for a Berkshire Conference in on History of Women.
Provenance
The Adelaide Johnson papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a loan in April 2015.
Biographical note
Adelaide Johnson, 1859-1955, was a suffragist, artist, and sculptor. Her original name was Sarah Adeline Johnson; she changed her name to Adelaide in 1878.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Printed materials, Photographs, Letters, and Exhibits.
General
Cataloged from items.
Suffragists -- United States.; Cabinet photographs; Suffragists -- Pictorial works; Albumen prints; Gelatin silver prints; Johnson, Adelaide, 1859-1955; Anthony, Susan B. (Susan Brownell), 1820-1906; Anthony, Susan B. (Susan Brownell) (Statues); Stanton, Elizabeth Cady; Stanton, Elizabeth Cady (Statues); Mott, Lucretia; Mott, Lucretia (Statues); Lisa Unger Baskin Collection (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library); Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- Printed Materials, 1891-1945 and undated; 3 folders
  Scope and Contents
  Includes printed materials gathered by Johnson in the course of her suffragist activity and artistic pursuits, including her own exhibitions as well as the sculpture of suffragists Mott, Stanton, and Anthony. There are programs, speeches, postcards, etchings, calendars and other published materials.
  - Johnson biographical material, 1909-1945 and undated; 1 folders (Box 1)
    Contains multiple copies of several printed items about Johnson or that mention her, along with a published undated photograph of her. Titles include: Sculpture Exhibition of portraits of eminent people by Adelaide Johnson At her studio and galleries.... 8-10 January 1909; American Lyceum Club..., Adelaide Johnson, Representative, N.Y., 1904; Adelaide Johnson, Sculptress, 1945. There are also notes written by her that refer to several items in this collection.
  - Speeches, pamphlets, postcards, etchings, and silhouettes, 1912-1921; 1 folders (Box 1)
    Includes printed items from Johnson's personal and working files of the period, including a brochure on Baroness Bertha von Suttner; a postcard featuring a portrait of Susan B. Anthony; a printed copy of Sara Bard Field's speech presenting Johnson's busts of Mott, Stanton, and Anthony to Congress; eight postcards of Johnson's plaster casts for the busts; and two silhouettes of Lucretia Mott. There are also published portraits and etchings of Susan B. Anthony, and copies of the program for Anthony's eighieth birthday party.
  - Suffragist and women's rights calendars, 1891-1918 and undated; 1 folders (Box 1)
    There are five calendars: Women's Literary Club, Dunkirk, N.Y. The women's calendar 1891 (Buffalo, N.Y.: Peter Paul and Brother, [1890?]); Catharine M. Fleming. The Anthony home calendar: with selections from the letters and speeches of Miss Anthony. Illustrated by Frances B. Johnson. (Washington, D.C.: n.p., 1900); Catharine M. Fleming. The Susan B. Anthony home calendar for 1902: with extracts from the letters and speeches of Miss Anthony. Portraits by Frances B. Johnson. (Washington, D.C.: n.p., 1901); Grace Hoffman White, compl. The Susan B. Anthony calendar 1918; quotations from her life and speeches. (New York, N.Y.: Barse & Hopkins, 1917); and Jane A. Stewart, arr. Birthday calendar (Perpetual) of suffrage women. (Philadelphia, Pa.: Current Syndicate, n.d.). The November page in the Stewart calendar contains a handwritten note by Johnson.
- Photographs, 1884-1905 and undated; 5 folders
  Includes photographs Johnson used for reference to create her sculpture of Lucretia Mott, Susan B. Anthony, and Elizabeth Cady Stanton that is located at the United States Capitol building, with focus on Susan B. Anthony. There are cabinet cards of her plaster casts, cabinet cards of Anthony and Anthony and Stanton, several signed, along with albumen, gelatin deveoping-out paper, and matte collodion printing-out paper prints of Anthony. There are two additional photographs, of Elizabeth Miller Jarvis and John A. Logan.
  - C. M. Bell cabinet cards for Johnson's bust of Susan B. Anthony, 1891?; 1 folders (Box 1)
    There are eight cabinet cards showing 4 different views of Johnson's plaster bust of Susan B. Anthony. They are undated, but Johnson's handwritten note on the back of one suggests the date as 1891. The C. M. Bell studio was in Washington, D.C.
  - Susan B. Anthony photographs, 1884-1905 and undated; 1 folders (Box 1)
    Contains 16 portraits of Susan B. Anthony, including 4x6.5-inch cabinet cards, along with albumen, gelatin deveoping-out paper, and matte collodion printing-out paper prints ranging in size from 3.5x5.5-inches to 4x6.5-inches. All but one feature profile views of Anthony, the other is a 3/4 view, and several of the images are signed and dated or otherwise inscribed by her or are identified on the negative by the photographer. Photography studios represented include Phillips (Philadelphia), C. M. Bell (Washington, D.C.), J.H. Kent (Rochester, N.Y.), F. Gutekunst (Philadelphia), Veeder (Albany, N.Y.), Mrs. L. Condon (Atlanta, Ga.), and Woodworth (Rochester, N.Y.).
  - Susan B. Anthony and Elizabeth Cady Stanton photographs, 1892; 1 folders (Box 1)
    There are three photogaphs showing Stanton and Anthony reviewing documents together. Includes two 4x6-inch cabinet cards and one 7.5x9-inch cabinet card; two of the photographs were signed and dated by both women. The studio for all three images was J. H. Kent, in Rochester N.Y.
  - Susan B. Anthony and others, 1893 and undated; 1 folders (Box 1)
    Includes two 3.5x5.5-inch cabinet cards. One undated photograph shows Susan B. Anthony (in profile) with her niece, Emma Sweet (3/4 view). The other is a seated full-length photograph of Susan B. Anthony (in profile) and Emily Gross (3/4 view), seated; both women signed and dated the item. The first photograph was taken at the Rice Studio in Washington, D.C. The second photograph was taken at the Max Platz Studio in Chicago.
  - Photographs of others, undated; 1 folders (Box 1)
    Includes two images possibly unrelated to other materials in the collection. There is an undated photograph of Elizabeth Miller Jarvis that was removed from a published piece, and an undated cabinet card by Baldwin and Ames Studio, Chicago, featuring a sculpture (probably Johnson's) of Union General John A. Logan.
- Letters, 1912-1939; 1 folders
  Includes seven letters written to Johnson while she resided in New York City, and in Rome, Italy. Includes a 1912 letter of introduction to her in Rome for a Mrs. Reynolds; two 1918 letters from a loving friend, "Little Mother," in England, one discussing the life of memories "that cannot be effaced" and news of the war from both the British and American perspective, followed by another letter celebrating the war's end; a 1919 letter to Johnson in Rome informing her there is no room in New York City to sublet, despite her excellent record as a tenant; a 1920 letter regarding Johnson's subscription to the New York Evening Journal; William Parker's letter of introduction for Johnson in her capacity as a Trustee of the Bacon Society of American, to the Bacon Society in London, England. Also includes a 1939 clipping from the New York Sunday Times that misidentified an image of Susan B. Anthony.
  - Letters, 1912-1939 (Box 1)
- Exhibits, 1986 or 1987; 1 folders
  There are twelve lablels for for the first exhibition to be held at Elizabeth Cady Stanton's House after it was acquired by the Women's Rights National Park at Seneca Falls, curated by Lisa Unger Baskin in 1986 or 1987, and featuring the Johnson materials. The exhibit was also displayed at the Sophia Smith Collection for a Berkshire Conference in on History of Women.
  - Exhibits, 1986 or 1987 (Box 1)